两年前
很多时候 当生命中重要的事情发生的时候
A lot of the time, you don't register
你并没有意识到它的重要性
the important moments in your life as they happen.
只有当你回头看的时候 你才发现它的重要性
You only see that they were important when you look back.
去他妈的安全带
Fuck seat belts.
我们怎么办
What should we do?
我们要在附近找个地方  舒服点的地方住下来
We need to find somewhere nearby, somewhere nice.
我的老天
Holy shit.
私闯民宅来保持低调你觉得合适吗
Is breaking and entering the best way of lying low?
我觉得就是他了 这个房子的主人
I think that's him, the guy that lives here.
我们可以在这里休息一下 不用着急
We can just chill here, take our time.
有时候我觉得James是值得爱的男孩子 真爱的那种
Sometimes James feels like a boy I could love, like, really love.
和Alyssa在一起让我开始有感觉了
Being with Alyssa had started to make me feel things.
- 你怎么进来的 - 拜托 不要
- How did you get in here? - Please don't.
他当时要伤害你 Alyssa
He was going to hurt you, Alyssa.
快他妈的开车
Fucking drive!
是我杀了他 她什么都没做
I killed him. She didn't do anything.
- 出发 - 告诉他们都是我一个人干的
- Move! - Tell them that I did it all.
这样你就会没事了
Then you'll be okay.
- 武装警察 - James
- Armed police! - James!
现在
情不知所起 一往而深
#  My love has no beginning My love has no end  #
爱若磐石 我心斐然
#  No front or back And my love won't bend  #
左右为难
#  I'm in the middle  #
碾转反侧
#  Lost in a spin  #
一往情深
#  Loving you...  #
而你不知 不知 不知
#  And you don't know, you don't know You don't know, you don't know...  #
Bonnie
Bonnie.
是你啊
It is you!
我是Ray 从圣约瑟夫来的
It's Ray. From Saint Joseph's.
我们在一个班上
We were in the same class.
我之前一直带着一个医用眼罩
I had, like, a... medical eye patch for a bit.
噢 对
Oh, yeah.
再拿一个那个
And one of those.
最近怎么样啊 有孩子了吗
So how are you? You got kids?
没有
No.
- 结婚了吗 - 没有
- Married? - No.
那你最近都在做什么
So what have you been doing?
坐牢
Prison.
噢 好吧
Oh, right.
你为什么会...
Why were you, uh...
你做了什么
What did you do?
我杀了个人
I killed someone.
故意的
On purpose.
好吧
Right.
扯淡
Shit.
我差点信了
You properly got me there.
被你骗了
You got me.
- 你的幽默感总是很古怪 - 是的
- You always had a weird sense of humour. - Yeah.
我现在准备再杀一个人
I'm gonna go kill someone else now.
- 需要袋子吗 - 不用 谢谢
- Do you want a bag? - No, thanks.
拜 Ray
Bye, Ray.
而你不知 不知  不知
#  And you don't know, you don't know You don't know, you don't know...  #
我有多开心
#  How glad I am...  #
去他妈的世界
我很小的时候就明白了什么是惩罚
I learnt about punishment from a young age.
我知道 惩罚也是出于爱
I learnt it happens because of love.
- 澳大利亚 - 维也纳
- Austria. - Vienna.
- 中国 - 北京
- China. - Beijing.
- 刚果民主共和国 - 金沙萨
- Democratic Republic of the Congo. - Kinshasa.
拉脱维亚
Latvia.
基辅
Kiev?
你这是在打我的脸
I feel like you've punched me in the face.
我妈妈一直想让我上大学
My mum always wanted me to go to university.
她没去成 因为怀孕了
She couldn't go because she got pregnant.
怀了我
With me.
她总是把我放在第一位
She always put me first.
鳕鱼
Cod.
又是鳕鱼
Again?
这有助于大脑发育
It's good for the synapses.
爸爸花很多时间打理院子
Dad spent a lot of time in the garden.
我17岁时 他失业了
When I was 17, he lost his job.
他不想告诉我们 所以他每天都照常上车
He didn't want to tell us, so every day he got in the car
开着转悠直到下班时间才回家
and drove around until it was time to come home.
当我妈发现的时候 她非常生气
When Mum found out, she was quite upset.
你是我的天使
#  You are my special angel  #
来自天堂
#  Right from paradise...  #
过了不久爸爸就离开了
Dad left soon after that.
我
I'm...
就是去弄点牛奶
just getting some milk.
妈妈说我们俩没有他会过的更好
Mum said we were better off without him.
妈妈
Mum?
这表示她可以把所有的精力都投入在我身上
It meant she could focus all her energy on me.
你从哪儿弄来这个的
Where'd you get this?
我找到的
I found it.
你知道什么样的女人才戴这种东西吗
Do you know what kind of women wear this?
妓女
Hookers.
妓女考试不会及格
Hookers don't pass exams.
吃了它
Eat it.
什么
What?
吃了
Eat...
它
it.
全吃了
All of it.
生活有时会很艰难
Life can be hard.
用嘴巴嚼烂
Make sure you chew.
妈妈教会我如何适应它
Mum taught me how to cope with it.
他妈的怪胎
Fucking weirdo.
怎么对付别人
How to cope with people.
我只能让你休学了
I'm gonna have to suspend you.
好的
Okay.
- 我可以留着这个吗 - 不行
- Can I keep that? - No.
我18岁的时候 所有的考试都挂科了
When I was 18, I failed all my exams.
妈妈其实也没多大反应
Mum was actually okay about it.
三个优
Three A's.
很好
Good.
而这并没有阻止我去大学
And it didn't stop me from going to university.
谢谢
Thanks.
我在大学工作
I got a job there.
你也是这儿的学生吗
You a student here as well?
有时一个不经意间的决定导致的后果会不堪设想
Sometimes a small decision can lead to something big.
- 是的 - 酷
- Yes. - Cool.
哲学系
非常严重的后果
Something really big.
我看见一只手
#  I seen a hand  #
我看见一个画面
#  I seen a vision  #
它在云端出现
#  It was reaching through the clouds  #
像一个梦境
#  To risk a dream  #
影子划过天际
#  The shadow crossed the sky  #
狠狠的砸向地面
#  And it crushed into the ground  #
像一个怪兽
#  Just like a beast  #
那老男人又回来了
#  The old man's back again  #
#  The old man's back again...  #
我可以借用一下吗
Uh, may I?
这是你们这学期的教科书
This is your textbook for the term.
别动
Don't move.
我们开始吧
Let's begin.
Foucault很丢人
Foucault is an embarrassment.
他没有地位
He has no class.
自由 是你对自己所经历的事采取的应对方式
"Freedom is what you do with what's been done to you."
Sartre
Sartre.
做你自己人生的主角
Be the protagonist in your own story.
这个故事以知识分子的反抗行动开始
And that story begins with an act of intellectual defiance.
读一下Max Weber和Erving Goffman的书
Read Max Weber, Erving Goffman.
如果你想要更现代一些的观点
Or if you want a more contemporary perspective,
这个人也不错
this guy's pretty good.
你不是学生 对吗
You're not a student, are you?
你只是在这里工作
You just work here.
人们争取到了来上我的课的权利
People have earned the right to come to my class.
而你没有
You haven't.
我不想再看到你 明白了吗
I don't want to see you again. Okay?
有时人们看不到你的潜力
Sometimes people don't see your potential.
所以你必须展示出来
So you have to show them.
是你干的吗
Was this you?
这是屎吗
Is this human shit?
是的
Yeah.
你的吗
Yours?
也许
Maybe.
你可以来上我的课 不过有个条件
You can come to my class... on one condition.
什么
What?
你陪我出去喝点酒
You have a drink with me.
每周一次
Once a week.
好的
Okay.
终于 我看到了自己的未来
Finally, I could see a future for myself.
这感觉不错
And it felt good.
我找到一个魅力之都
#  I found a place full of charms  #
是宝贝臂弯里的魔法世界
#  A magic world in my baby's arms...  #
去吧
Go ahead.
她柔软的拥抱像绸缎和蕾丝
#  Her soft embrace like satin and lace  #
奇妙的地方
#  A wondrous place  #
我们不再疑心
#  We're above suspicion  #
你和我
#  Both you and I  #
他们说我是个好姑娘
#  They say that I'm a good girl...  #
坐
Take a seat.
而我是个好男人
#  And that I'm a good guy  #
你喜欢这个吗
Do you like this?
不太喜欢
Not really.
那...
So...
跟我说说你自己吧
Tell me about yourself.
不
No.
好吧
Okay.
为什么你想要来上我的课
Why did you want to take my class?
感兴趣
I was interested.
对什么感兴趣
In what?
对人生的意义
In what the point is...
对一切
of anything.
那你为什么不上学
Why aren't you a student?
- 你很聪明 - 我挂科了
- You're clearly bright. - Failed my exams.
考试就是区分不同程度的平庸 仅此而已
Exams rank different levels of mediocrity, that's all.
出色的人考试都考不好
Exceptional people don't do well at them.
我就考不好
I didn't.
你很漂亮
You are very pretty.
你知道吗
Do you know that?
有人告诉过你吗
Do people tell you that?
你是条小三文鱼 对吗
You're a little salmon, aren't you?
什么
What?
你想要逆流而上
You want to swim against the tide.
我们要不把衣服脱了吧
Should we take our clothes off?
打个车吧
Take a taxi.
谢谢
Thank you.
你知道吗
Do you know something?
什么
What?
我可能会爱上你
I could fall in love with you.
他像铅一样沉重 宝贝
#  He's as heavy as a lead weight, baby  #
他像线般纤细
#  He's as skinny as a wire...  #
那事已经发生了吗
Has it happened yet?
什么
What?
爱上我
The love.
快了
Nearly.
但我们今天晚上就到这
But we're finished for tonight.
他像一个妖术娃娃
#  He's got a heavy kinda hoodoo, baby  #
他会诅咒你
#  And he can lay it on you  #
他会把诅咒说的好像
#  He can say it like...  #
我给出了我的真心
#  I gave you my heart  #
在很久很久以前
#  Long, long ago  #
我已经收不回来
#  I can't take it back  #
亲爱的 知道吗
#  Darling, you know...  #
你待我不好
#  How you treat me mean  #
我要还这几本书 然后借这几本
Just, uh, returning these and getting this one out.
这个真的很棒
This is really good.
是啊 这是我最喜欢的
Yeah, it's my favourite.
嗯
Yeah.
你说德语吗
So you speak German then?
- 是的 - 太棒了
- Yeah. - Oh, cool.
好吧
Okay.
很好
Great.
谢谢
Thanks.
这人是谁
Who was that?
他想要做我男朋友
He wants to be my boyfriend.
他约我明天晚上去吃芝士火锅
He asked me to a fondue night tomorrow.
那你要去吗
Are you gonna go?
我喜欢芝士
I like cheese.
我想给你拍些照片
I'd like to take some photographs of you.
什么
What?
明天晚上来找我吧
Come and see me tomorrow night.
今晚怎么样
How about tonight?
今晚不行
I can't do tonight.
当你想要什么的时候
When you want something,
等待就很漫长
it's hard to wait.
你会失去耐心
You can get impatient.
她是谁
Who is she?
- 噢 我不想让你担心 - 什么
- Oh, I didn't want to worry you. - What?
我只在课堂上见过她
I'd only seen her in lectures.
我都不知道她的名字
I didn't know her name
后来 几周前她来找我
until she came to see me a couple of weeks ago.
我太蠢了
I was stupid.
居然同意和她单独谈谈
Agreeing to talk to her alone.
她说她很担心她的考试
She said she was worried about her exams.
我相信她了
I believed her.
她很明显是爱上我了
She's clearly in love with me.
然后想着她又编一些谎话
And now she's made up these lies.
她威胁我
She's threatening me.
她要告诉大家我侵犯了她 她想要毁了我
She's gonna say I attacked her. She wants to destroy me.
毁了我的生活 我的事业 所有的一切
My life, my work. Everything.
这姑娘疯了
The girl's mad.
所以那些话都不是真的
So it isn't true?
你怎么可以问我这样的问题
How can you ask me that?
- 不 不是 我不是这个意思 - 滚出去
- No, look, I didn't... - Get out.
滚出去
Get out!
爱能让你清楚的知道什么是对什么是错
Love makes you feel quite clear about what is right and what is wrong.
当有人做错了事情时 就要受到惩罚
And when someone has done something wrong, they have to get punished.
噢
#  Ooh  #
顺着路一直走
#  Walk down a road  #
和我一起走
#  With me  #
走出去
#  Walking out  #
我就在这里
#  I'm here for  #
从我的脑海中消失
#  Getting out of my head  #
为了更好的开始
#  Making plans for a better  #
做一个计划
#  Beginning  #
我需要急救车
Ambulance.
这里发生了意外
There's been an accident.
它发生了
我爱上了你
Clive
这条路很长
#  It's a long road...  #
你之前让我跟你聊聊我自己的事情
You asked me to tell you about myself that time,
我说了不
and I said no.
我现在想要告诉你了
I want to tell you now.
我从很小的时候就明白了什么是惩罚
I learnt about punishment from a young age.
而且我知道惩罚是出于爱
I learnt it happens because of love.
我以前一直觉得我可能不是真实存在的
I used to feel like I maybe wasn't real.
就好像我是凭空捏造出来的一样
Like I was made up of nothing.
但坠入爱河之后 空虚感逐渐
But when you fall in love, the nothing feeling
被有些感觉给吞噬
is eaten by a something feeling,
或者说 被所有的感觉给吞噬
which is eaten by an everything feeling.
你吞噬了我
You swallowed me,
让我自由了
and set me free.
你怎么知道这里是安全的
How do you know that this one is safe?
没有明显的监控摄像头
No obvious burglar alarm.
到处都是灰尘 所以应该没有清洁工会来
Dust everywhere, so no cleaner to worry about.
邮件
Post.
至少有一个星期的量了
At least a week's worth.
私闯民宅来保持低调你觉得合适吗
Is breaking and entering the best way of lying low?
飞离
#  Fly away  #
什么
What?
情不知所起 一往而深
#  My love has no beginning My love has no end  #
爱若磐石 我心斐然
#  No front or back And my love won't bend  #
左右为难
#  I'm in the middle  #
碾转反侧
#  Lost in a spin  #
一往情深
#  Loving you  #
而你不知 不知 不知
#  And you don't know, you don't know You don't know, you don't know...  #
嗨
Hi.
Alyssa在吗
Is Alyssa in?
爱比天高 爱比海深
#  My love has no bottom My love has no top  #
高出天际 深入海底
#  My love won't rise And my love won't drop  #
左右为难
#  I'm in the middle  #
无从终止
#  And I can't stop  #
一往情深
#  Loving you  #
而你不知 不知 不知
#  And you don't know, you don't know You don't know, you don't know...  #
吾心欣然
#  How glad I am  #
翻译-Sukey 校对-仓央嘉措的粉丝